"What Is Titanium Dioxide, and Is It Safe?"
Food-grade titanium dioxide,
also called E171,
is used extensively
in food products
as a whitening agent
in things like chewing gum
and some maybe
not-so-obvious products,
like baked goods and candy.
In a survey of foods
from a U.S. grocery store,
white frostings,
coffee creamers, and chewing gum
had the highest concentrations,
followed by some candies,
almond and rice milks,
and dairy products,
like skim milk, sour cream,
and yogurt.
And the tricky part in the U.S.
is food additives
like titanium dioxide
are allowed to be listed
generally as "color added"
or as an anticaking agent
or filler.
So, you may not actually know
what foods contain it.
This is exactly
what the food survey found.
High amounts of titanium dioxide
in some foods with no labeling
indicating the product
even contained titanium dioxide.
The only reason we care
is because of risk.
Titanium dioxide
has been approved
as a safe color additive
for use in foods and drugs
in the United States
since 1966
and the European Union
since 1969,
until the European Food Safety
Authority (known as EFSA)
concluded in 2021
that titanium dioxide, E171,
can no longer be considered safe
as a food additive.
What changed?
Based on all
the evidence available,
a concern for genotoxicity,
damage to our DNA,
could not be ruled out.
As a result of this report,
the European Union prohibited
its use as a food additive
in August 2022.
Since the 2021 report
was issued,
the U.S. Food
and Drug Administration
has been petitioned
to no longer allow the use
of titanium dioxide in foods,
but that is still pending.
Other international
food regulatory organizations,
like those
in the United Kingdom,
Canada, Australia,
and New Zealand,
also do not agree
with EFSA's assessment
and still allow
titanium dioxide in foods.
Why all the differing opinions?
The FDA notes that some
of the genotoxicity tests
considered by EFSA
don't represent
the titanium dioxide
used in foods.
Food-grade titanium dioxide
is a mixture
of microsized particles
and nanosized particles.
Nanoparticles
are tiny materials
ranging in size
from 1 to 100 nm.
That's about 100,000 times
smaller than a human cell,
which is what
the genotoxicity studies
in animals were done with.
A common theme voiced
by those disagreeing with EFSA
is that you can't compare
nanoparticle toxicity studies,
where researchers mixed
and dispersed the nanoparticles
in a fluid,
with titanium dioxide in foods
that rely
on bigger microparticles
for the desired
color appearance.
What about
the 40% nanoparticles?
Well, when you mix nano
and microparticles together,
a nano might glom
onto a microparticle;
so, it might not
have the same effect
as a straight nanoparticle.
So, on the one hand,
the European Union
considers no amount
of food-grade titanium dioxide
in food to be safe,
banning its use
and setting off
a worldwide chain reaction
with bans in other countries
including Switzerland, Qatar,
and most recently, Turkey.
Meanwhile, other countries
including the U.S.,
UK, and Canada
don't consider the evidence
for a ban compelling.
DNA damage isn't
the only problem though.
Very little
of the titanium dioxide we eat
is actually absorbed,
but when it is,
it may just sit there
and accumulate over time.
But what happens to the 99%
that isn't absorbed?
It ends up in our colons,
where it can damage colon cells,
and this
is the food-grade additive.
It may also have adverse effects
on our gut microbiome,
based on studies using just
titanium dioxide nanoparticles,
as well as the mixed version
used as a food additive.
There are nontoxic ways
for food companies
to whiten their products,
like rice starch or rice flour,
but for the same effect,
more needs to be used,
increasing costs.
If you live in a country
like the U.S.
where it's still legal,
what should you do?
In my mind, there should
be an extremely high bar
for safety
for cosmetic additives.
And that's what
titanium dioxide is,
basically white food coloring.
Since it is in no way necessary,
and tends to be used
in ultra-processed junk food,
we recommend trying to avoid it.
Even if it were
eventually exonerated,
it would still be better
to use soy milk
than dairy coffee creamer
and to choose oatmeal
over powdered donuts.